<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>St Pauls challenge, or The Churches triumph: in a sermon, preacht at the Fort-Royal March 3. 1643. By Jer: Leech. And now published at the request both of the generous; and his much honored friend captaine George Dipfort.</title>
            <author>Leech, Jeremiah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E49_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859065</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859065</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111126</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111126)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 9:E49[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>St Pauls challenge, or The Churches triumph: in a sermon, preacht at the Fort-Royal March 3. 1643. By Jer: Leech. And now published at the request both of the generous; and his much honored friend captaine George Dipfort.</title>
                  <author>Leech, Jeremiah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Paine, and are to be sold by Francis Eglesfield at the Marigold in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "may 27.".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans VIII, 31 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111126:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>PAVLS</hi> CHALLENGE, OR THE CHVRCHES TRIVMPH: In a Sermon, Preacht at the FORT-ROYAL <hi>March</hi> 3. 1643.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Jer: Leech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now publiſhed at the requeſt both of the generous; and his much honored friend Captaine <hi>George Dipſort.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EZEK. 22.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Can thy heart endure, or can thy head be ſtrong in the day that I ſhall deale with thee?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Paine,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Francis Eglesfield</hi> at the <hi>Marigold</hi> in <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:111126:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111126:2"/>
            <head>S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>PAVLS CHALLENGE,</hi> OR The Churches Triumph.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROMANS 8 v. 31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If <hi>GOD</hi> be for us, who can be againſt us?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Triumphant Challenge of a Victorious Champion, againſt all the Churches enemies, bodily and ghoſtly. It was daringly done of <hi>Goliah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.10.</note> when he challenged the whole Hoaſt of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Loe here, all the Hoaſt of the earth are challeng'd, with all the Armies of Hell to boote, and though they ſhould all joyne in one, here's one that defies them all. The Triumph is firſt <hi>more generall,</hi> in this verſe and in the next. Then <hi>more particular,</hi> in the verſes that come after; which I ſhall touch upon anone. In this verſe, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> triumphs, that nothing can befortun a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to doe him any hurt. The reaſon, becauſe God is of his ſide, <hi>God is for him. If God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi> In the next verſe, he triumphs againe, that nothing can be wanting to a Chriſtian that ſhall doe him any good. The reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath Chriſt given him; and Chriſt being given him, what can be denied him? <hi>He that hath given us Chriſt, how ſhall he not with him give us all things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing againſt us? All for us? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaies the Apoſtle?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111126:3"/>
               <hi>what ſhall we ſay to theſe things?</hi> Theſe are ſuch things, as if all were reckon'd up, that can be reckoned up, nothing could be more ſaid. He ſummes up all here that he had ſaid before. Before, he had enumerated and reckon'd up, the ſeverall, and ſingular priviledges, that Chriſtians have an intereſt in. He beginnes with the loweſt of them, <hi>Deliverance from condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> In de firſt verſe of the chap. <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt.</hi> And then he goes on, till he comes to the higheſt; from the ſtate of condemnation, out of which we are delivered, to the ſtate of <hi>glorification,</hi> unto which wee are exalted. He hath <hi>praedeſtinated us,</hi> (he ſaies) He hath <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led us,</hi> He hath <hi>juſtified us,</hi> He hath <hi>glorified us;</hi> So in the v. immediatly before going. But there he ſtayes, hee makes a ſtop at that, as if when he had ſaid that, he had ſaid all; He had gone ſo high as he could goe no higher. And therefore here, by way of recapitulation, he breaks forth into this <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant acclamation,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; what ſhall wee ſay to theſe things? As if he ſhould ſay, This is all that can be ſaid. More then this cannot be ſpoken; greater comfort then this, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be given. You may underſtand it three waies. Either by way of <hi>thankefull acknowledgement; What ſhall we ſay to theſe things?</hi> They be ſuch excellent things, as wee can never bee ſufficiently thankfull to God for them. Or by way of <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and wonderment: what ſhall we ſay to theſe things!</hi> They be ſuch wonderfull things, as wee cannot but admire and bee aſtoniſhed, ſo often as we thinke of them. Or laſt of all, by way of <hi>triumph and challenge What ſhal we ſay to theſe things?</hi> They be ſuch high and mighty things, as we dare challenge all Creatures, Men and Devills, to ſay or doe what ever they can againſt them; we are confidently reſolved, and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily wee conclude, that nothing can be againſt us, as long as God is for us. <hi>If God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words, as they lie, conſiſt of two parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>A Suppoſition.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>An Interrogation.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>Suppoſition</hi> in the firſt words. <hi>Si Deus pro nobis, If God be for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111126:3"/>
            <p>The <hi>Interrogation,</hi> in the next: <hi>Quis contra nos?</hi> who can be againſt us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If God be for us,</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle. The word <hi>If,</hi> is not to be <hi>doubtfully,</hi> but <hi>affirmatively</hi> taken. Though it have but a <hi>ſuppoſitive forme,</hi> yet it hath a <hi>poſitive force.</hi> Commonly it is ſpoken, I know, of things that are <hi>queſtionable:</hi> yet ſometime of things that are <hi>impoſſible;</hi> ſometime of things that are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitable</hi> Things that are <hi>impoſſible.</hi> So <hi>Gal</hi> 4.8. <hi>If an Angell from heaven preach any other Goſpel, then that which wee have preacht, let him be accurſed.</hi> The Apoſtle knew it was <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible</hi> that an Angell from heaven ſhould preach any other Doctrine; yet he ſuppoſes a <hi>poſſibility,</hi> therefore expreſſes it by an <hi>If.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as things <hi>impoſſible</hi> thus; ſo thus, things <hi>indubitable and certaine.</hi> They are expreſt by an <hi>If</hi> too, which ſometime carries the force of an <hi>Etſi, although.</hi> Sometime of a <hi>Quoniam, Becauſe. If</hi> thus; That is, <hi>Although</hi> thus. As 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1. <hi>If any man ſin.</hi> The Apoſtle knew there was not any man but did ſin: But his meaning was, that <hi>Though</hi> a man did, yet he had <hi>an Advocate to the Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or againe, <hi>If</hi> thus; That is, <hi>Seeing</hi> thus, or <hi>Becauſe</hi> thus: As here in my Text, <hi>Si Deus pro nobis, If God be for us;</hi> That is, <hi>Quoniam Deus pro nobis; Becauſe</hi> God is for us, Or <hi>Seeing</hi> God is for us.</p>
            <p>And ſo for the <hi>Interrogation</hi> that followes; The <hi>quis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra nos? who can bee against us?</hi> The Apoſtle meant not to grant, that <hi>ſome might be,</hi> but rather concluded that <hi>none could be. Who can?</hi> As much to ſay, as <hi>None can.</hi> Like that of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Pſal.</hi> 130.3. <hi>If thou Lord ſhalt marke our iniquities, Quis feret? who can abide it? Ille quis, nullus;</hi> ſaies S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> That's as much to ſay, as <hi>None can abide it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So here, <hi>If God be for us, Quis contra nos? who can be againſt us? Ille quis nullus;</hi> The meaning of that is, <hi>None can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us.</hi> As the <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> before, had the force of a <hi>Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> implying that <hi>Gods being for us,</hi> was not a thing to bee <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> only, but <hi>granted:</hi> ſo this <hi>Interrogation</hi> here hath the force of a <hi>Negative;</hi> implying that <hi>becauſe God is for us,</hi> that there can be any thing againſt us, is not a thing to be <hi>queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> but flatly <hi>denyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:111126:4"/>
            <p>In a word; That which the Apoſtle would ſay here, is plainly this. <hi>Nothing can be againſt thoſe; nothing can hurt thoſe, with whom, or for whom God is.</hi> The words are <hi>argumentative;</hi> and the Apoſtles argument in them, is <hi>Syllogiſtically</hi> framed. We have an <hi>enthymeme</hi> here, a <hi>contracted Syllogiſm. God is for us: Ergo, none can be againſt us.</hi> Or if you will, a <hi>Hypotheticall Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme;</hi> the <hi>Major</hi> only expreſt: The <hi>Minor</hi> and <hi>Concluſion</hi> conceald. Fully thus. <hi>If God be for us, none can be againſt us.</hi> This is the <hi>Maior</hi> part of the Syllogiſme, and this you ſee is expreſt. Then comes in the <hi>Minor,</hi> though <hi>conceald</hi> in in the text, <hi>but God is for us.</hi> Thereupon the <hi>Concluſion</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follows, <hi>Therefore none can be againſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being the <hi>ſcope</hi> of the words, the <hi>parts</hi> ſhall be theſe. Not a <hi>Suppoſition</hi> and a <hi>Queſtion,</hi> as before; but a <hi>Propoſition</hi> and a <hi>Proofe:</hi> Or if you pleaſe a <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and a <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 1. You have here a <hi>Propoſition</hi> or <hi>Doctrine;</hi> In effect this; <hi>None can be againſt thoſe that are Gods.</hi> 2. You have the <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Proofe</hi> of it, <hi>Becauſe God is on their ſide, God is for them.</hi> Both theſe we ſhall diſcourſe upon; upon the <hi>Doctrine</hi> firſt; then upon the <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and having done with the <hi>explication</hi> of them, we will conclude with the <hi>uſe and application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If God be for us, who can be againſt us? Who can be againſt us,</hi> does the Apoſtle aske? He needed not aske that, you will ſay. If we compare number with number, we ſhall find more <hi>againſt us then for us.</hi> We have thoſe that are <hi>openly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us;</hi> and we have thoſe that are <hi>ſecretly against us;</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies <hi>againſt us</hi> from <hi>without,</hi> and enemies <hi>againſt us</hi> from <hi>within;</hi> as many <hi>againſt us</hi> as Chriſt had <hi>againſt him.</hi> Looke how many <hi>wicked men</hi> there be in the world, ſo many we have <hi>againſt us.</hi> Looke how many <hi>Devils there be in hell,</hi> ſo many we have <hi>againſt us.</hi> And yet does the Apoſtle aske, <hi>who can be againſt us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who knowes not, that there hath beene enmity from the beginning, between the <hi>ſeede of the Woman, and the ſeede of the Serpent?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> Who knowes not, how <hi>he that was borne after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was borne after the ſpirit? And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo it is now,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. As it was then, ſo is it now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It was then ſo, and it is now ſo. Now
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111126:4"/>to this day the matter is not mended a whit; nor the world is no Changeling, but ſtill the old quarrell is renewed and maintained. They that were againſt Chriſt then, are againſt Chriſt ſtill; They that perſecuted the Church then, perſecute it ſtill. In the <hi>infancy</hi> of it, it was perſecuted by <hi>Tyrants;</hi> In the <hi>growth</hi> of it, it was perſecuted by <hi>Hereticks;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard</note> Now in the <hi>peaceable times</hi> of it, it hath beene perſecuted by <hi>falſe brethren, and hypocriticall Profeſſors.</hi> Even in our owne dayes a ſort that have ſeem'd to be greatly <hi>for the</hi> Church, they have beene ſhamefully <hi>againſt</hi> it; againſt the ſpirituall glory of it, againſt the ſincere worſhip of God in it, againſt the power of the Goſpell, and the purity of the ordinances, (more for <hi>Innovation</hi> then for <hi>Reformation</hi>) though for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſplendour and ceremony, zealous beyond meaſure, to advance the pompe of it. Of her being perſecuted by theſe three enemies, the Church may complaine as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, when he fear'd to be deprived of his three ſonnes: <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph is not, and Simeon is not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 42.36.</note> 
               <hi>and now they will take Benjamin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way too; All theſe things are againſt me.</hi> So the poore Church of Chriſt may complaine; Tyrants have perſecuted me, and Hereticks have perſecuted me; and now falſe brethren and hypocrites perſecute me: What Rocks am I caſt upon? what ſtraites am I driven to? All theſe things are againſt me. And yet does the Apoſtle aske, <hi>Who can be againſt us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of queſtion, as long as there is a Chriſt in heaven, and a Church on earth; there will be a Devill in hell, and a faction in the world, that will maintaine warre againſt both. Unleſſe Chriſt and the Devill could be reconciled, the world and the Church will never be at peace; They are <hi>strangers</hi> one to another. Chriſtians are ſtrangers in the world: Therefore they muſt looke for no friendly entertainment in it, but to be uſed as ſtrangers. Nay they are <hi>enemies,</hi> hating and hated one of another. <hi>The world hates me,</hi> ſaies <hi>our</hi> Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and <hi>therefore it will hate you:</hi> And it is well it does ſo. It's a good providence of God that the world ſhould hate us, that ſo we might learne to be out of love with the world. How were the Prophets hated and perſecuted in it?<note place="margin">Joh. 15.18.</note> How were the Apoſtles hated and perſecuted in it? Even this our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111126:5"/>Apoſtle, St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe after he had once taken upon him the name of a Chriſtian, he never went without the badge of a Chriſtian, but carried the croſſe about with him ever-after,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.17.</note> bore the markes of it in his fleſh to his dying day. What ever place he came into, he met with one or other, that was <hi>againſt him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.32. Act. 19.24.</note> with <hi>Beaſts at Epheſus that fought againſt him;</hi> with <hi>Demetrius the Silver-ſmith</hi> that <hi>raiſ'd the Citie in uproare againſt him;</hi> with <hi>Alexander the Copper-ſmith,</hi> that did all the miſchiefe he could to him;<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.13. 2. Tim. 4.10. Act. 13.8. Act. 14.19. Act. 16.22.</note> with <hi>Alexander the Copper-ſmith,</hi> that did all the miſchiefe he could to him; with <hi>Demas</hi> that revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him; with <hi>Elymas at Paphos, that withſtood him;</hi> with the <hi>Jews at Lyſtra, that ſton'd him;</hi> with the <hi>Magiſtrates at Philippi, that whipt and impriſoned him;</hi> with multitudes at <hi>Jeruſalem, that charged heavy and falſe accuſations upon him;</hi> and at Rome laſt of all,<note place="margin">Act. 21.28.</note> with <hi>a Nero that</hi> beheaded him; and yet doth this Man aske, <hi>who can be againſt us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes; He might aske it well enough. Take S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> words, and we may confidently reſolve this <hi>Interrogative,</hi> into a <hi>Negative; None can bee againſt us:</hi> That is to ſay, None can be ſo againſt us, as ever to prevaile againſt us. They may <hi>Aſſault,</hi> but they cannot <hi>overcome:</hi> They may <hi>oppoſe,</hi> but they cannot <hi>overthrow;</hi> They may <hi>fight,</hi> but they cannot <hi>foile;</hi> They may ſhake, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>ſhiver:</hi> They may <hi>wound,</hi> but they cannot <hi>kill;</hi> or they may <hi>kill,</hi> but they cannot <hi>hurt;</hi> kill the body, but not kill the ſoule: In a word, They may <hi>beleaguer,</hi> but they cannot <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer;</hi> Traitor-like <hi>undermine us,</hi> but not <hi>blow us up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Premimur, non opprimimur,</hi> it is the <hi>Churches Motto;</hi> the word that ſhe carryes in her Flag and Enſigne. As 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8. <hi>We are troubled on every ſide, but yet we are not diſtreſſed; we are perplexed, but yet we doe not deſpaire; we are perſecuted, but yet we are not forſaken; we are caſt down, but yet we are not deſtroyed.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 129.1. <hi>Many a time they have afflicted me from my youth, may Iſrael now ſay: Many a time they have afflicted me from my youth; Sed non praevaluerunt, but they have not prevailed againſt me.</hi> No, they ſhall never doe that: It is the <hi>Apoſtles Challenge</hi> here in my text. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? <hi>who can be againſt us?</hi> That is, <hi>who ſo, as to prevaile againſt us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three things you may be pleaſed to take notice of, in the words.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:111126:5"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The Perſons to whom.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Perſons for whom.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>The matter about what.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To whom, or againſt whom,</hi> the Apoſtle makes this chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge. I anſwer, To all the Enemies of the Church, be they who they will be. The word <hi>Tie, who,</hi> is a <hi>comprehenſive</hi> word; takes in all, excepts none; neither <hi>ſpirituall</hi> enemies, <hi>nor bodily.</hi> Not <hi>ſpirituall;</hi> ſuch as would <hi>accuſe,</hi> verſe 33. ſuch as would <hi>condemne,</hi> verſe 34. ſuch as would <hi>ſeparate us from God,</hi> verſe 35. None ſhall be able, either to doe the one of theſe, or the other; not ſin, not Satan, not the Law, not our own conſciences. Let them attempt what they will, what they can; none of them ſhall prevaile againſt us. No nor any <hi>bodily</hi> enemies neither: Thoſe that he afterward muſters up. <hi>Tribulation, diſtreſſe, perſecution, famine, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, perill, ſword.</hi> Theſe though they may infeſt and endanger the body, threaten to make conqueſt of us that way; yet when they have done all they can doe, in ſtead of conquering us, we ſhall conquer them; nay, <hi>we ſhall be more then conquerours</hi> over them, ſaies the Apoſtle, <hi>through him that loves us;</hi> in the 37. verſe of the chapter.</p>
            <p>He goes a ſtep higher yet; joynes <hi>bodily and ghoſtly both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether;</hi> bids defiance to them all, heroically reſolves that none of them all ſhall prevaile; neither <hi>death nor life, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to com, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature;</hi> let them make what confederacies they can, joyne all their counſells, and forces together; yet they ſhall never be able <hi>to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Thus you ſee, who they are, <hi>againſt whom</hi> the Apoſtle makes his challenge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Obſerve <hi>for whom,</hi> or in whoſe behalfe he makes it. That's in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s;</hi> who againſt <hi>us?</hi> Which you may either underſtand to be <hi>generally</hi> meant, of <hi>the whole Church;</hi> or <hi>particularly,</hi> of <hi>every Member</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againſt the whole Church</hi> firſt of all,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.25. Pſal. 125.1.</note> none ſhall ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile. It is <hi>a houſe built upon a rock.</hi> Let the raine fall, let the windes blow, let the flouds riſe, her foundation is impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and (as the Pſalmiſt of Mount-Zion) <hi>ſhall never be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111126:6"/>moved.</hi> Tis true. The Church is ſometime like a Ship upon the Sea,<note place="margin">Iſai. 54.11.</note> 
               <hi>afflicted and toſſed with tempeſts.</hi> Like the Ship that the Diſciples ſayl'd in, <hi>fill'd with water, and cover'd with waves,</hi> and the paſſengers,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.26.</note> all ready to cry out, <hi>Lord ſave us, we pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi> We have had the ſad and woefull experience of it, in all ages. And even of late <hi>dayes,</hi> what preſſures the Church hath ſuffered, in moſt places of Chriſtendome, how the ploughers have ploughed long furrows upon their backs, how her fields have been ſowne with the bodies, &amp; watered with blood of Gods Saints, the <hi>Goſhens</hi> and <hi>Edens</hi> of it, that were ſometimes as the Gardens of God, turn'd now into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celdemaes</hi> and <hi>Golgothaes,</hi> (I would I could ſay that we in our owne land had not beene made to drinke deepe of this cup) whoſe heart bleeds not to thinke of it? Certainly in many places, the Enemies have mightily prevailed. I, but yet for all this, though they have prevailed over <hi>ſome part</hi> of the Church; over <hi>the whole Church</hi> they ſhall never prevaile; though over <hi>the perſons,</hi> yet never <hi>over the cauſe.</hi> She ſhall have an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi</hi> ſtill, a <hi>hiding place</hi> to reſt in, though it be in <hi>the wilderneſſe.</hi> God will ſtill reſerve a remnant to himſelfe, even in the worſt times, that ſhall worſhip him in ſincerity, and not <hi>kiſſe the Calves in Bethel,</hi> nor <hi>bow the knee to Baal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, Though the Churches Enemies may now and then prevaile in ſome places; yet like the Sea (as one ſaies) what they <hi>gaine in one place,</hi> they <hi>loſe in another.</hi> And ſo the Church for her part, what ſhe <hi>loſes in one place, ſhe gaines in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</hi> As what ſhe loſt among the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the Goſpell of Chriſt, ſhe gain'd among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> when they received it. So what ſhe loſt in the <hi>Eaſterne parts</hi> of the world, ſhe gained in the <hi>Weſterne;</hi> what ſhe loſt in <hi>Garmany,</hi> ſhe gain'd in the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> what in <hi>Italy and Spain;</hi> ſhe gain'd in <hi>France and England.</hi> God ſtill ſo provides, that what her Enemies doe <hi>againſt her</hi> in one place, he does <hi>for her</hi> in another; and though they prevaile <hi>againſt ſome</hi> part of the Church, <hi>yet againſt the whole Church</hi> (as I ſaid) they ſhall never prevaile.</p>
            <p>Nay; they ſhall never prevaile neither <hi>againſt any one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church.</hi> Every childe ſhall inherit the ſame bleſſing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111126:6"/>with the Mother. What Chriſt ſaid unto <hi>Peter,</hi> is ſhall be verified upon every Diſciple of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.31. <hi>Satan hath deſired to winnow thee, as wheat is winnowed, but I have prayed for thee, that thy faith may not faile. Peters</hi> Faith never utterly faild; Tis true, It was ſhaken indeede, but though <hi>concuſſa,</hi> yet not <hi>excuſſa,</hi> as <hi>Theophylact</hi> ſayes, though it were <hi>ſhaken,</hi> it was not <hi>ſhiver'd; Mota, ſed non amota, moved</hi> it was, but it was not <hi>removed: Coepit areſcere, ſed non exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit;</hi> It <hi>withered at the</hi> top, but it <hi>dyed not at the roote.</hi> In 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of a <hi>Crowne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> that he ſayes he knew <hi>the Lord would give him.</hi> Marke what he adds; He ſayes he would <hi>not give it to him only,</hi> but to <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that loved his appearing.</hi> Had not every Chriſtian this priviledge, his condition were uncomfortable. But our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe is, that what ever God or nature hath intended for the ſafety and conſervation of the whole, ſhall be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated and diſtributed to every part. If therefore no Enemie ſhall ever prevaile <hi>againſt the whole Church;</hi> I being a member of the Church, my confidence and comfort is, that none <hi>ſhall ever finally prevaile againſt me.</hi> Let's aſſure our ſelves, they ſhall not. Though they may prevaile over our <hi>lives,</hi> they ſhall not prevaile over our <hi>ſpirits.</hi> Though they may reproch our names, and plunder our eſtates, and mangle our bodies; they ſhall never doe any violence to our ſoules. No, the Devill himſelfe ſhall never lay hand upon them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he could <hi>pluck them out of Gods hand.</hi> He may <hi>bruiſe them with tentation,</hi> but he ſhall never <hi>bring them to deſtruction. God has made us invincible, though he have not made us invulnerable.</hi> So thus you ſee the ſecond point; <hi>For whom,</hi> or in whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe the Apoſtle makes this challenge.</p>
            <p>In the third and laſt place; Obſerve the matter about which he makes it. About the enemies <hi>being againſt the Church.</hi> Who <hi>can be againſt us?</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle. That's the <hi>challenge</hi> he makes. And how <hi>againſt</hi> us, he ſpecifies in three particulars. 1. In the 33. verſe. <hi>Quis accuſabit? Who ſhall accuſe Gods elect? or who ſhall lay any thing to their charge?</hi> None ſhall be able to doe that. He tells you why. Becauſe it is <hi>God that juſtiſies us.</hi> God is the Judge of all, and it is in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111126:7"/>Judges power to pronounce thoſe that are accuſed, either guilty or innocent. If God being the Judge, therefore will juſtifie us to be innocent, no accuſer can make us guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>Then in the 34. verſe. <hi>Quis condemnabit? Who ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne?</hi> None ſhal be able to doe that neither: He tells you why. Becauſe <hi>Chriſt is dead and riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n againe for us.</hi> Chriſt by his death and reſurrection hath acquited us from the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of condemnation. He became ſurety for us, and paid the debt that we owed. The death that we deſerv'd he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and being ſuffered by him, it cannot be charged upon us. What ever debt I owe, my Creditour cannot condemne me in it, if he that undertakes to be my ſurety, have paid and diſcharged it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, in the 35. verſe, <hi>Quis ſeparabit?</hi> ſays the Apoſtle. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of God?</hi> Nor ſhall any be able to doe that either. He tells you why. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Gods love in Chriſt is unchangeable, therefore nothing can ſeparate from it.</hi> Many occaſions may ſeparate friends here, and cauſe a diverſion of their love.<note place="margin">John. 13.1. Jam. 1.17.</note> But <hi>whom God loves, he loves to the end:</hi> His love is as Himſelf is, ſubject to no varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>I am perſwaded nothing can ſeparate us from the love of God to us in Chriſt,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſweetly in the cloze of this chapter. If then there be none that can <hi>accuſe</hi> us, none that can <hi>condemne</hi> us; none that can <hi>ſeparate us from God, or God from us;</hi> we may boldly make the challenge that the Apoſtle here makes; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Who can be againſt us?</hi> Afflicted the poore Church may be (as you heard before) but who ever <hi>afflicts</hi> her, none can <hi>overcome</hi> her. Enemies may <hi>riſe up againſt her,</hi> but none of the ſhall <hi>prevaile againſt her.</hi> That is, they ſhall never ſo prevaile, as either to <hi>pervert</hi> her, or <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> her. They ſhall neither ſcare her from her profeſſion, nor ſupplant her from her peace. They ſhall neither bereave her of her Faith, nor deprive her of the reward of her Faith. They ſhall neither ſtrip her of Grace, nor ſpoile her of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>I may goe one ſtep higher yet. So far ſhall the Enemies of the Church be from doing any thing <hi>againſt her,</hi> as in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111126:7"/>ſeeking to doe <hi>againſt her,</hi> the ſhall rather doe <hi>for her.</hi> In ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to be her <hi>Enemies,</hi> they ſhall (though againſt their wills) prove her <hi>beſt friends.</hi> What ever they intend to <hi>her hurt,</hi> it ſhall turne to <hi>her good.</hi> As <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to his brethren,<note place="margin">Gen. 50.20.</note> 
               <hi>When you thought evill againſt me, God meant it to my good.</hi> So God will turne that to the good of his Church, which her Enemies intend to her for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill. The plot that <hi>Haman</hi> laid for <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and the lot that he caſt for the rooting out of the Jewes, beſide the miſchiefe he brought upon himſelfe by it, (it was like an Arrow ſhot upright, that fell downe upon his owne head) it turn'd in the end to <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai's</hi> greater advancement, and to the <hi>Iewes</hi> greater enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And ſo ſhall every thing turne, that the Enemie plots and practiſes, to ruine any of Gods children, it ſhall turne to their greater good and glory in the end. It may for the time helpe to let out ſome of their corrupt blood; but they ſhall afterward be the ſounder for it. As it was with <hi>Phereus Iaſon</hi> in the ſtory; one that had an Apoſthem growing within his body;<note place="margin">Cic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deor: l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> when an Enemie of his that thought to have killed him ran at him with his ſword, it ſo happened in the thruſt, that the ſword did only prick the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtheme; and by that meanes <hi>profuit hoſtis,</hi> his Enemie did him a better turn, then all his Chirurgions could doe him. <hi>Gladio vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micam aperuit;</hi> He opened the ulcer he had within him, and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening it cured it.</p>
            <p>They ſay vines beare the better, when they are watered with blood: So does the vine of Gods Church. The blood that has been ſhed in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> has been a deaw to water it. The more the Church has been perſecuted, the more ſhe has flouriſht. Like the Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mill, the more you treade upon it, the thicker it growes;<note place="margin">Nitit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r in pondus palma et conſurgit in altum.</note> like the Palme; the more weight you lay upon it, the broader it ſpreads. <hi>Non minuitur, ſed augetur,</hi> ſaies <hi>Leo.</hi> The Church leſſens not with perſecution, but increaſes. Therefore <hi>Tertullian</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> when they were ſo cruell in perſecuting the poore Chriſtians. What gaine you by all your cruelty? ſaies he. It is no ſuch Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to ſcare us, it is rather a Baite to allure us. <hi>Quoties metimur, plures efficimur;</hi> the oftner we are mowen downe, the thicker we come up. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> found it ſo, when he oppreſt and afflicted the Iſraelites; <hi>The more he afflicted them,</hi> ſaies the text, <hi>the more they mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied and grew. Exod.</hi> 1.12. And <hi>Herod</hi> found it ſo after his <hi>behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Iames, and impriſoning of Peter.</hi> The <hi>fiercer</hi> he waxt, the <hi>fertiler</hi> the Church waxt, for (ſays the ſtory) <hi>the word multiplyed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111126:8"/>and grew after it. Act.</hi> 12.24. We neede not wonder at this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved. No wonder that nothing can prevaile againſt the elect of God; nothing to <hi>accuſe;</hi> nothing to <hi>condemne;</hi> nothing to <hi>ſeparate</hi> them from his love. The Apoſtle gives a ſatisfactory reaſon for it here in my text: It is becauſe <hi>God is on their ſide; God is for them.</hi> Which brings me to the <hi>proof</hi> of the <hi>Propoſition;</hi> the ſecond gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall part that I propounded to ſpeake of. <hi>Si deus pro nobis; If God be for us;</hi> that is, <hi>Quoniam Deus pro nobis; Becauſe God is for us;</hi> therefore none <hi>can be againſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>none can be againſt us,</hi> becauſe <hi>God is for us,</hi> is a reaſon ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragable. All power ſave Gods, is but a created power, therefore but finite and limited; Onely Gods is infinite and un-limited, be-becauſe un-created: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſays <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> The God that we have is above all Gods. And <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſays <hi>Cyril,</hi> The power that God has, is above all power. Now if that power be <hi>for us,</hi> that is above all power; and if the <hi>God be for us,</hi> who is above all Gods, impoſſible it is, that as long as we have him <hi>for us,</hi> any thing can be <hi>againſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was part of <hi>Moſes</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſong of triumph that he ſung after <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt were diſcomfited in the Red ſea; <hi>Who is like unto thee oh Lord among the Gods, who is like unto thee? Exod.</hi> 15.11. They ſay the <hi>Machabees</hi> had it afterward for their Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and put it upon their banner when they went out to their warrs.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mi Camocha, Baelim Jehova. Who is like unto thee oh Lord among the Gods?</hi> And thence it was, as the <hi>Hewrews</hi> report, that they had their name given them; namely from the initiall letters of the foure words in that ſentence, <hi>Mem, Caph, Beth, Jod,</hi> which are juſt the initiall letters of the foure ſyllables of their name, <hi>Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baei.</hi> Sufficient it is that God hath cal'd himſelfe <hi>El-ſhaddai;</hi> a God al-ſufficient. So to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>Eni, El-ſhaddai, I am the Almighty God;</hi> or I <hi>am God all-ſufficient. All-ſufficient</hi> to himſelfe. <hi>All-ſufficient</hi> to his Creatures. <hi>All-ſufficient</hi> to ſave. <hi>All-ſufficient</hi> to deſtroy. <hi>All-ſufficient</hi> to doe what he will. <hi>All-ſufficient</hi> to doe how he will. <hi>All-ſufficient</hi> to doe more then he will. Having therefore ſuch a God <hi>for us;</hi> a God almighty, a God all-ſufficient; a God like unto whom there is no God; none like him in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, none like him in holineſſe, none like him in juſtice, none like him in mercy, none like him in truth, none like him in power; in defiance to all enemies, bodily and ghoſtly, ſecret and open. Traytours and Rebells, Hereticks and Tyrants, Jeſuites and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111126:8"/>wee may confidently make it our triumph and our chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, <hi>If God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves, out of the verſe before-going,<note place="margin">De verbis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postoli. Serm. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> that God may be <hi>ſaid</hi> to be <hi>for us</hi> foure wayes. For us in <hi>predeſtinating</hi> us; For us, in <hi>calling</hi> us; For us in <hi>iuſtifying</hi> us; For us in <hi>glorifying</hi> us. And theſe foure wayes, by which God is ſaid to be <hi>for us,</hi> he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to thoſe foure Enemies that riſe up <hi>againſt us.</hi> The firſt, our <hi>inferiour</hi> Enemies; (as he calls him) that's <hi>Man.</hi> The ſecond our <hi>exteriour;</hi> that's the <hi>World.</hi> The third our <hi>Interiour;</hi> that's the <hi>Fleſh.</hi> The fourth our <hi>ſuperiour;</hi> that's the <hi>Devill.</hi> That man cannot prevaile againſt us, he argues; becauſe of Gods predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us. Nor the world; becauſe of Gods calling us. Nor the fleſh; becauſe of Gods juſtifying us. Nor the Devill; becauſe of Gods glorifying us. None of all theſe can be <hi>againſt us, if God be for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſtead of, <hi>If God be for us;</hi> ſome reade, <hi>Si deus nobiſcum; If God be with us.</hi> And being ſo read, it may ſeeme to have ſpeciall refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For <hi>Immanuel</hi> you know is <hi>Chriſts</hi> name; and that's as much to ſay as <hi>Deus nobiſcum; God with us.</hi> And indeed, it is moſt certaine, that <hi>Gods being for us,</hi> it does properly and prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily come from Gods being <hi>with us.</hi> It comes originally from <hi>Chriſt.</hi> It is in and through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that God does all thoſe things for us, that you heard of, that he <hi>predeſtinates,</hi> and <hi>calls,</hi> and <hi>iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies,</hi> and <hi>glorifies.</hi> It is in and for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake, that none can <hi>accuſe</hi> us, <hi>condemne</hi> us, <hi>ſeparate</hi> us from his love. He is the fountaine of all that love, with which it pleaſes God to embrace us. And as all the promiſes, ſo all the bleſſings we enjoy, they are all as ſtreames flowing from that fountaine. All our liberties, priviledges, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, graces; all our ſafety, ſtrength, peace, joy; all our preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from dangers, ſupportations in dangers, deliverances out of dangers; In a word, all the good that God has done us; all the good that he intends to doe us, all muſt be acknowledged to come by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and by him, praiſe to God muſt be rendred for all; even by him that is our <hi>Immanuel, God with us;</hi> and by his being <hi>with us,</hi> ſo <hi>for us,</hi> as that nothing can be <hi>againſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All we have now to examine is no more but this; wherein God hath ſo declared himſelfe to be <hi>for his Church,</hi> as in times of feare and danger, ſhe may be bold to ſecure her ſelfe under his protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and confidently reſolve, while he is <hi>with</hi> her, and <hi>for her,</hi> none can be <hi>againſt her.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:111126:9"/>
            <p>I anſwer: God has abundantly done it ſeverall wayes; and thoſe both ordinary, and extraordinary. Ordinarily he has done it <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſuppeditando,</hi> by ſupplying her with ſuch a proportionable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of power and ſtrength, as ſhe has beene able to deale upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall termes with the ſtrongeſt of her Enemies, and to make her part good with them, in their hotteſt conflicts and aſſaults, for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, for puiſſance, for number, for power, it has many times falne out, that the Churches proviſion, have not beene a whit inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to any of her Enemies.</p>
            <p>But his extraordinary wayes are more remarkeable. God has many times uncouth and extraordinary wayes, ſuch as none could ever have expected, invented, imagined, to bring his worke and purpoſe about, as for the peace and ſafety of his Church, ſo for the diſſipation and confuſion of thoſe that have beene her Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He has done it, <hi>animos conciliando;</hi> by meekning the hearts of her Adverſaries, and by ſweetly attempering them to a placid and peaceable diſpoſition.<note place="margin">Pro. 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>When the wayes of a man pleaſe the Lord,</hi> ſayes <hi>Solomon, he will make his Enemies his friends. Eſau,</hi> though he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the <hi>heart of an Enemie</hi> toward <hi>Jacob,</hi> yet he ſhall looke upon him when he meets him, with the <hi>face of a friend.</hi> The ſtroakes and wounds that perhaps he intended, and threatned, they ſhall be turned into kiſſes and ſmiles. You ſee what a ſtrange way he brought the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of their <hi>Babylonian captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 126.4.</note> The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſayes, <hi>He turned their captivity like the water of the South.</hi> And how was that? That was by the thawing of the Snow that had lyen all the winter frozen and congeald upon the tops of the Icie mountaines. When at the returne of the Spring, the heate of the Sun had melted and diſſolved it, it brought ſtore of waters down into the dry places of the South, ſo turned the barren deſarts of it into ſtanding pooles. Thus God turned the captivity of his people. He cauſed the hearts of thoſe heathen Princes, <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> and the reſt under whom they had beene held Captives, to relent and melt toward them, ſo as they licenced them to depart, and to returne peaceably into their owne land. And no leſſe ſtrangely by the Chriſtians, in the times of the primitive Church, when they had ſuffered long perſecution under trucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and bloody Tyrants; God at laſt mollifyed their hearts, made them of <hi>Wolves</hi> to become <hi>Lambs,</hi> enclined divers of thoſe perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Emperours, <hi>Adrian,</hi> and <hi>Traian,</hi> and <hi>Severus,</hi> and others,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111126:9"/>out of tender compaſſion to recall thoſe cruell edicts, that they had publiſhed againſt the poore <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> not ſuffering them to be executed with ſuch rigour, as formerly they had beene, and in the end reſtored peace to his Church.<note place="margin">Pro. 21.1.</note> 
               <hi>He that hath the hearts of all men in his hand, can turne them, as he pleaſes, like rivers of waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He does it, <hi>terrorem incutiendo,</hi> by ſtriking terror and feare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hearts of the enemy, that they dare not drive on, to do the miſchiefe they would doe. In <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.28. <hi>I will ſend the hornet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee,</hi> ſays the Lord, <hi>that ſhal drive out before thee the Hivite &amp; the Canaanite.</hi> What <hi>Hornet</hi> was it that he meant? See the verſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore going; <hi>I will ſend my feare before thee, and will deſtroy all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to whom thou ſhalt com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The terrour and feare with which God often ſtrikes the hearts of his enemies it is like the <hi>ſting of a Hornet,</hi> that takes away their ſpirit and courage from them, and makes them <hi>flee when none purſues them.</hi> Thus in <hi>Jehorams time,</hi> when the <hi>Syrians</hi> with a huge Army came to make warre againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Reg. 7.6.</note> God made them <hi>heare a noyſe of Chariots, and a noyſe of Horſes:</hi> &amp; the very feare of this ſo amaz'd them, as they left all they had in their tents, and fled for their lives.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.2.</note> Thus <hi>Saul</hi> was reſtrain'd from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any hurt unto <hi>David,</hi> by reaſon of the feare that God ſtrake his heart withall. <hi>He was afraid of David,</hi> ſaies the text, <hi>becauſe he ſaw that the Lord was with him.</hi> And thus the Iews were reſtrained,<note place="margin">Luke 19.47.</note> even <hi>for f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re of the people,</hi> from laying hands upon Chriſt, when they would have apprehended, and put him to death. Strange to ſee, how great ones doe many times ſtand in feare of thoſe that are meaner then themſelves, thoſe who, one would think, ſhould rather ſtand in feare of them; and how few in number God can make to diſperſe exceeding great multitudes. As <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſaid to his <hi>Armour-bearer,</hi> when they two, and no more, creeping upon their hands and knees, betweene the teeth of thoſe two rockes, that were in <hi>Bozez</hi> and <hi>Seneh,</hi> diſcomfited a Garriſon of the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims; There is no restraint to the Lord to ſave by many, or by few.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 14.6.</note> God promiſed his people that it ſhould be ſo; that he would ſtrike ſuch feare into the hearts of their enemies, that <hi>five of them ſhould chaſe a hundred, and a hundred of them put ten thouſand to flight. Levit.</hi> 26.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He does it <hi>poenam infligendo;</hi> by inflicting ſome remarkable judgement upon the enemy. Sometime, for the <hi>preſent diſabling</hi> of them; as it was with <hi>Jeroboam</hi> when he ſtretcht forth his hand againſt the Prophet at <hi>Bethel,</hi> commanding to <hi>lay hold on him,</hi> his hand withered and dryed up by and by, ſo that hee was <hi>not able
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111126:10"/>to put it in againe.</hi> And ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Theodor. hiſt. Eccl. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alens</hi> the Emperor, when hee came to ſigne the writ for the baniſhment of Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi> his fingers ſhook and ſhrunke up that he was not able to hold the pen. Sometime againe to <hi>the utter cutting off,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>and deſtroying of them.</hi> So when <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> and his hoſt of uncircumciſed <hi>Aegyptians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.25.</note> purſued the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> at the red Sea;<note place="margin">2 Reg. 19.35.</note> 
               <hi>God ſtrooke off their Chariot wheeles,</hi> and the Sea cloſed her mouth upon them, that <hi>they ſunke as leade into the mighty waters.</hi> So <hi>Senacherib,</hi> and his <hi>Aſſyrian Army, a hundred and five thouſand</hi> of them, when they came to fight againſt <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> they were by an <hi>Angell of God all ſlaine in one night, and all found in the morning ſo many dead corpſes.</hi> Many examples you ſhall meet with in the <hi>Eccleſiasticall Hiſtories,</hi> of the prodigious and fearefull judgements that almighty God ſent upon perſecuting Tyrants, and of the miſerable ends that they came unto; by meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Church enjoyed tranquillity and peace.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He does it <hi>curſum divertendo;</hi> by diverting the courſes of the enemy, and putting them upon new occaſions, to ſtay the preſent violence of their furious proceedings. Thus when <hi>Saul</hi> was purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 23.27.</note> hunting him up and downe <hi>like a Partrich upon the mountaines;</hi> God ſprung up a new game for him (as one ſaies) ſet the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> upon the back of him, ſo as hee was faine to leave chaſing of <hi>David,</hi> and to bend his forces againſt them. We want not thoſe in our owne times that may in this example reade their owne ſtory; men that have beene hot in the purſuing of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, others that have beene as innocent perhaps as ever <hi>David</hi> was, and by them as much hated (I dare ſay) as ever <hi>Saul</hi> hated <hi>David,</hi> when by all the projects and practiſes they could deviſe, they have endeavored the treading of them downe, and the roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them up; ſodainly the wheele has turned about, and while they have beene undermining others, others have countermined againſt them, ſo as they have been forced to leave the game they were following, and to ſhift for the ſaving of their owne skins. I neede not inſtance in thoſe of the <hi>Popiſh faction.</hi> It's notoriouſly well knowne, how active they have alwaies beene, ſpecially of late yeeres, how induſtriouſly, how indefatigably they have beſtir'd themſelves, for the ſtrengthening of their confederacy and advancing of their cauſe, making <hi>no-bodies</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> or worſe then <hi>no-bodies.</hi> But I hope there is a <hi>Weſterne winde</hi> now blowing, that will turne their weather cocks another way.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He does it <hi>machinas detegendo;</hi> by detecting and diſcloſing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111126:10"/>the machinations and plots of the enemy; and ſo ſtrangely bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to light, that they have been defeated, before they could be accompliſht. Thus the plots of the <hi>Aramites</hi> were diſcovered, even their <hi>bed-chamber ſecrets</hi> to the <hi>Prophet Eliſha.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Reg. 6.12.</note> Thus the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of <hi>Bigthan</hi> and <hi>Tereſh,</hi> two of the <hi>Kings Chamberlains</hi> was diſcovered by <hi>Mordecai</hi> to King <hi>Ahaſhuerus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſter 2.22.</note> Thus the plot that <hi>Haman</hi> had laid againſt <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and the lot he had prepared to deſtroy the whole nation of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> was diſcovered to <hi>Queene Eſther,</hi> and by a ſtrange providence prevented. Thus the conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie againſt <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 23.12.</note> by above <hi>forty men</hi> that had bound themſelves <hi>with an oath and a curſe, neither to eate nor drink till they had killed him,</hi> was diſcovered to the <hi>Chiefe Captaines by his Siſters Sonne.</hi> And thus the plot of our <hi>Gunpowder Traytours</hi> (the like whereof heaven never ſaw, hell never forg'd, earth never heard of) was diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the writing of a letter, I know not whether more ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pen'd, or ſtrangely interpreted; but pen and tongue both guided by a Divine providence, to bring thoſe dark things to light which (had they beene otherwiſe) our light had beene cover'd under per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall darkneſſe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Conſilia infatuando,</hi> by infatuating the counſels of the enemy, and <hi>turning their deviſes into fooliſhneſſe.</hi> Thus the Lord infatuated the counſaile of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> which hee had ſo politiquely and ſo peſtilently contrived againſt <hi>David.</hi> Certainly, had that perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious peece of Counſaile ſucceeded, the field had been halfe wonne before a blow had been given. But God that guided the tongue of <hi>Huſhai,</hi> guided alſo the heart of <hi>Abſalom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 17.14.</note> and made <hi>Huſhais</hi> counſaile to prevaile with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> that <hi>Abſaloms</hi> treaſon might not prevaile againſt <hi>David.</hi> So what he intended for a ſnare to <hi>David,</hi> it proved in the concluſion a halter to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>All theſe waies it pleaſeth Almighty God ſo to declare himſelf for the defence and protection of his Church, as while hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares <hi>for her,</hi> ſhe may boldly bid defiance to any enemies that can come in <hi>againſt her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I have given you the <hi>Explication</hi> of my text as well as I am able. I ſhall now onely crave leave, to wind up what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in a word or two of <hi>application;</hi> and then diſmiſſe you with a bleſſing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If it be ſo, that while <hi>God is for us, none can be againſt us;</hi> all that are Gods have here a ſtrong foundation of comfort to build upon: Let who will be <hi>againſt thee;</hi> the world <hi>againſt</hi> thee, the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111126:11"/>Devill <hi>against</hi> thee, all <hi>againſt</hi> thee, as long as thou haſt <hi>God with</hi> thee, thou needeſt not be diſmaid; <hi>Thou haſt more with thee then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee,</hi> as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to his ſervant, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.16. be confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that unleſſe they can overcome God, they can never overcome thee. When <hi>Caeſar</hi> was at Sea in a great tempeſt, the Maſter of the ſhip began to bee afraid; The Emperour bad him not bee afraid; <hi>Caeſarem vehis,</hi> ſays he remember thou haſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> in the Ship with thee: Whereſoever we are, ſo long as we have <hi>God with us,</hi> there's nothing we have cauſe to be afrayd of indeed. <hi>Pone me juxta te;</hi> ſo the vulgar reads that text <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.3. <hi>Set me beſide thee, and let any mans hand fight againſt me.</hi> The Prophet <hi>David</hi> heroically, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.1. <hi>God is our refuge and our ſtrength, therefore I will not feare though the earth be moved, though the mountaines be carried into the midſt of the ſea:</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.3. <hi>Though an hoaſt ſhould encample againſt me my heart ſhould not feare, though warre ſhould riſe up againſt me, yet in this I would be confident.</hi> In this? In what? He tells you in the firſt verſe; <hi>The Lord is my light and my ſalvation, therefore whom ſhould I feare? The Lord is the ſtrength of my life, therefore of whom ſhould J be afraid?</hi> Say a thouſand dangers compaſſe thee about:
<q>Mille mali ſpecies, mille ſalutis erunt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As thou haſt a thouſand dangers to environ thee, ſo God has a thouſand wayes to deliver thee. What could <hi>Luther</hi> ſay? If all the houſes in <hi>Wormes</hi> were tyled with Devils, I would not be afraid to goe thither; becauſe he was confident he had God to goe along with him. <hi>Deus meus et omnia,</hi> as he ſaid, <hi>God mine, and all mine.</hi> Let me but make that ſure, and whereſoever I become I am ſafe. If I can but be ſo happy as to apprehend that I have a propriety and intereſt in God, and to be aſſured that <hi>God is mine;</hi> though it be the nature of feare to betray all ſuccours, that will ſuccour me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all feares. God is a <hi>Rock</hi> to his children; what ever elſe we build upon, is but <hi>ſand;</hi> The <hi>Salvation</hi> of thoſe that truſt in him; Therefore <hi>David</hi> joyns them together, <hi>My God and my ſalvation, Salvation is mine, if God be mine.</hi> But then I muſt be able to ſay, he is <hi>Mine, Tolle meum, tolle Deum;</hi> take <hi>my</hi> away, as good take <hi>God away.</hi> Were it not for that poſſeſſive <hi>My,</hi> the Devill might ſay the Creed, to as good purpoſe as thou. For the Devill beleeves there's a God; the Devil beleeves there's a Chriſt; but that which torments him is this, that he cannot ſay <hi>My</hi> to any one article. Who ever can ſay that, and ſay it in Faith, he ſhall have that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort given him that all the world cannot take from him; even that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111126:11"/>
               <hi>ſpirit of comfort that ſhall abide with him to the end,</hi> and make him victorious in all his encounters. Nothing ſhall be forcible inough to bereave him of it. <hi>Sicut non vincitur qui dat, ita nec aufertur quod dat.</hi> As he that gives cannot be overcome, ſo that which he gives cannot be taken away. I remember it was the comfort that <hi>Moſes</hi> gave the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when they were to have warre with the <hi>Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites; Numb.</hi> 14 <hi>Feare not, God is with us.</hi> And <hi>Vegetius</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eget. lib.</hi> 3. cap. 3.</note> it was the word, that the <hi>Roman Souldiers</hi> afterward cheat'd up one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with in their wars; <hi>Deus nobiſcum; God is with us.</hi> Let it be your word alſo, when you goe forth into the field, and while you lye here in your Fort: Where ever you are, learne to doe by this text as <hi>Chytraeus</hi> reports the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> to have done.<note place="margin">Chytraeus in Itinerario.</note> He ſays, he was ſo taken with it, and ſo exceedingly admired it, as he cauſed it to be ſet in letters of Checquer-worke, upon a table that he commonly din'd and ſupt at, that having it alwayes in his eye, he might alwayes have it in his minde; <hi>Si Deus nobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, quis contra nos? If God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A here is a great deale of comfort, for them that are Gods, ſo for them that have no aſſurance of God, no propriety nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in God, here's a great deale of terrour.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>They can have no peace within themſelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>They can have no hope to prevaile againſt thoſe whom they count their Enemies.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>No peace within themſelves.</hi> For granting this to be true on the the one ſide, that <hi>If God be for us, none can be againſt us;</hi> the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry muſt needs be true on the other ſide, that <hi>if God be againſt us, none can be for us.</hi> Such the condition of all wicked men. They have <hi>God againſt them:</hi> And what can be more fearfull?<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.2.</note> 
               <hi>Hide not thy face from me,</hi> ſays David, <hi>nor abſent thy ſelf in a time of trouble.</hi> For God to doe that, <hi>to hide his face from us</hi> at any time, or (though a friend) to <hi>abſent himſelfe from us,</hi> we ſhall find that bad enough. But for God to looke at us with <hi>angry face,</hi> that will be ten thouſand times worſe. If to <hi>abſent himſelfe from us,</hi> be uncomfortable; <hi>to ſet himſelfe againſt us,</hi> that's a great deale more terrible. As we can have no <hi>friend</hi> like God, ſo we can have no <hi>Enemie</hi> like God. As it is no matter whom we have <hi>againſt us,</hi> if God be for us; ſo no matter whom we have <hi>for us,</hi> if God be <hi>againſt us.</hi> To ſay truth, all will be <hi>againſt us,</hi> if God be <hi>againſt us.</hi> Men <hi>against us,</hi> Angels <hi>againſt us,</hi> Devils <hi>against us,</hi> our owne conſciences <hi>againſt us,</hi> all Creatures in Heaven and Earth <hi>againſt us,</hi> and all too potent, too ſtrong for us:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111126:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111126:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:111126:13"/>
               <hi>Mice</hi> were too ſtrong for the <hi>Philiſtims; Lice</hi> too ſtrong for the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> when God had once ſet himſelf <hi>againſt them.</hi> So that's one part of wicked mens miſery, <hi>They can have no peace within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">A ſecond is; <hi>They can have no hope to prevaile againſt thoſe, whom they count to be their Enemies.</hi> The wicked count all their Enemies that are Gods friends. Therfore as they ſet themſelves <hi>againſt God,</hi> ſo they ſet themſelves <hi>againſt them.</hi> But all in vaine, and without hope of ſucceſſe:<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Why doe the heathen rage,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt? <hi>Or why doe the rulers of the earth combine and take counſaile together? They doe but imagine a vaine thing.</hi> And marke the reaſon that he gives; They doe it <hi>againſt the Lord, and againſt his anointed.</hi> The Lord will be too hard for them, and they will but <hi>kick againſt a throne,</hi> when they riſe up againſt him. So the Prophet, in <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.9. <hi>Aſſociate your ſelves oh you people, yet you ſhall be broken to pieces; and gird your ſelves, yet you ſhall be broken to pieces; Take counſaile together, yet it ſhall come to nought, ſpeake the word, yet it ſhall not ſtand:</hi> and it is the ſame reaſon he gives for it; <hi>Quia Deus nobiſcum, becauſe Gods is with us.</hi> God that ſits in heaven is alwayes with his Church, and when he ſees how actively her Enemies beſtirre themſelves, how they bend their bowe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.2.</note> 
               <hi>and make their arrow ready upon the ſtring, to ſhoote at them, that be upright in heart, videt, et ridet, He ſees them and laughs</hi> at them, <hi>breaks their ſnares aſunder, cuts their cords to pieces,</hi> many times <hi>catches them in their owne net,</hi> and makes them <hi>fall into the pit that themſelves have digged.</hi> How often falls it out, that the <hi>Churches deliverance and her Enemies deſtruction</hi> meete both together? How often that the plots which are layd for Gods children, are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſappointed, but the wicked themſelves undone by the plots that they have layd? Thence thoſe two phraſes of the Scripture, <hi>they weave the ſpiders web, and hatch the Cockatrices egge. They weave the ſpiders webbe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.5.</note> that ſhewes how vaine their attempts are. For how ſoone is the <hi>ſpiders web ſwept away,</hi> though never ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and curiouſly ſpun? So all the ſtratagems and attempts of the Churches wicked Enemies, though never ſo cunningly contrived, yet they are quickly defeated, ſcattered and ſwept away on the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, even <hi>like a ſpiders web.</hi> But that's not all; It's worſe then ſo. <hi>They hatch the Cockatrices egge:</hi> That ſhewes, how pernicious their attempts are, pernicious to their owne ſelves. For out of the <hi>egge they hatch,</hi> there ſprings a <hi>Viper</hi> that ſtings them to death. Their owne counſails and devices worke to their owne ruine. So it is a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111126:13"/>double evill that attends them, enough one would thinke, to cure them of their madneſſe, and to take them off from proſecuting their malicious purpoſes, when they begin to ſet their hearts upon miſchief; Firſt that they are <hi>vaine</hi> in what they do; then that they are <hi>curſt</hi> in what they doe. Firſt they ſhall be diſappointed in the circumventing of others; then the ruine that they ſtudy and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, ſhall fall upon their owne heads. In briefe; <hi>Thoſe for whom God is, nothing ſhall be againſt them; Thoſe againſt whom God is, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall be for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly and laſtly. Seeing <hi>while God is for us, nothing can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us;</hi> Beloved, it we deſire to have <hi>God for us,</hi> we muſt reſolve to be <hi>for God.</hi> We muſt be <hi>on his ſide,</hi> if we will have him <hi>on ours.</hi> What ſaid the Prophet <hi>Azariah</hi> to the men of <hi>Benjamin and Judah?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 25.2.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is with you, while you are with the Lord.</hi> Shall we thinke the Lord will be <hi>for us,</hi> if we be not <hi>for him?</hi> Nay, ſhall we thinke the Lord will be <hi>for us,</hi> when we are <hi>againſt him?</hi> while we ſide with the Devill and the world and the fleſh, can we be ſo unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable as to preſume that God will ſide with us? No. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what <hi>Davids</hi> words were to <hi>Solomon;</hi> 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.9. <hi>If thou ſeeke the Lord, he will be found of thee, but if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for ever.</hi> I would this leſſon were well remembred and well learnd. Sure I am; no people under Heaven have more cauſe to remember it and learne it then we. Never was God more <hi>for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> people, then <hi>for us</hi> in this land. How many eminent tokens and ſeales of his favour hath he printed upon us? How many mercies have we beene compaſt about withall? What plenty have we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd? What dayes of peace have we ſeene? What a happy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment have we lived under? What a flouriſhing ſtate have we had? What a flouriſhing Church have we had? What a ſort of mighty preſervations, and miraculous deliverances have we had? It were eaſy for me to loſe my ſelfe in this field, but it is too late to wander farre. I ſhall only exhort you to be mindefull of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we all ſtand engaged in. Seeing God hath been ſo <hi>gratious to us,</hi> let us be as <hi>zealous for him.</hi> Seeing he hath appeared <hi>on our ſide,</hi> let us appeare <hi>on his.</hi> And remember we cannot be rightly <hi>for God,</hi> if we be not <hi>againſt thoſe,</hi> that are <hi>againſt God.</hi> Gods friends muſt be our friends, and Gods Enemies muſt be our Enemies. Enemies they are to God, that are Enemies to his Church, Enemies to his cauſe, Enemies to his Goſpell, Enemies to the ſincerity of his worſhip and to the purity of his Ordinances. None more malevolent, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111126:14"/>bitter then thoſe of the <hi>popiſh faction,</hi> thoſe that are <hi>Romes fav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites;</hi> therefore none that we ſhould ſet our ſelves <hi>againſt,</hi> more then <hi>againſt them.</hi> We have beene faulty this way. We have <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed too much with Rome,</hi> and <hi>connived too much at Popery.</hi> Like thoſe of <hi>Thyatira</hi> (St. <hi>John.</hi> blames them for it) we have ſuffered <hi>the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Jezabel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>which calls her ſelfe a Propheteſſe, to teach and to deceive many of</hi> Gods <hi>ſervants; and to make them drunke with the cup of her ſpirituall fornication.</hi> It is time to un-deceive them if we can; to plucke the cup from their mouthes, and to plucke downe her from her throne. All that are on Gods ſide will doe it. <hi>Who is on my ſide there?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Reg. 9.33.</note> ſays <hi>John, Who?</hi> He that is on my ſide, let him caſt downe <hi>Jezabel:</hi> So, who ever is on Gods ſide, let him downe with that <hi>Jezabel of Rome,</hi> downe with her Idolatries and ſuperſtitions; downe with her trumperies and vanities; downe with her Altars and Images; down with her rags and reliques. They be but <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> fragments, and let them be uſed, as <hi>Jezabel</hi> was uſed; It's time they were troden under foote, and that <hi>Dogs-meate</hi> were made of them. Helpe <hi>Royall Soveraigne</hi> to throw her downe; Helpe more and more to throw her downe, You of the honourable court of <hi>Parliament.</hi> Every one that loves the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> helpe to throw her downe. Never let us halt (as we have done) betweene God and <hi>Baal,</hi> away with ſuch halting. Never let us mingle lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages as we have done, the <hi>Language of Aſhdod, with the language of Canaan.</hi> Away with ſuch canting. Let's ſpeake our ſelves what we are, and be no more aſhamed of our livery then we are of out ſervice. If we be aſhamed of Chriſt now, he will be aſhamed of us another day; but he will not refuſe to owne us, if we be not afraid to owne him. Ours he is, and ours he will be. He will be for us, he will be with us; with us in health and with us in ſickneſſe, with us at home and with us abroad, with us in the City and with us in the field, with us in peace and with us in warre, with us in life and with us in death. And we at laſt ſhall be with him (if we conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neu to be for him) in that glory and bleſſedneſſe which ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to all eternity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
